<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"/usr/share/xml/docbook/schema/dtd/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="common_popups">
<title>Common Popup Dialogs</title>
<para>
The module "Popup.ycp" contains commonly used popup dialogs for
general usage. Use those dialogs rather than creating your own custom dialogs
whenever possible.
</para>
<para>
If you have your own definitions of equivalent popups (which is very likely),
please remove them as soon as possible and use the popups from
"Popup.ycp". The new popups usually require fewer parameters - e.g. you
no longer need to explicitly pass standard button labels like "Yes" or "No"
etc. as parameters (we had to do that because of technical limitations with the
translator module, but we found a workaround for that).
</para>

<section>
<title>Simple and Expert Version</title>
<para>
There are several versions for each type of popup, a simple version with a
minimum number of parameters and one or more "expert" versions where you can
pass lots of parameters to fine-tune many details.
</para>
<para>
Use the simplest version one whenever you can. It's normally the version that
makes most sense for most cases.
</para>
<para>
If you use an "expert" version, try to stick to the default behaviour (i.e. the
behaviour of the simple version) as closely as possible. Change only parameters
you really need to change. In particular, only change the default button for
very good reasons.
</para>
<para>
If there is a specialized simple version, use it whenever you can. For example,
use <link linkend="Module_Popup_Warning">Popup::Warning</link>
rather than <link linkend="Module_Popup_AnyMessage">Popup::AnyMessage</link> with the same message if you
want to display a warning. This way we can make sure all warnings look the same
and make them easily recognizable as warnings.
</para>

</section>
<section>
<title>
Headlines, Yes or No?</title>
<para>
Sense or nonsense of providing headlines for each popup is a cause for endless
discussion - we've been through that. Sometimes headlines make sense, sometimes
they don't.
</para>
<para>
As a general rule of thumb, don't provide a headline that is more or less the
same as the message itself, i.e. don't
</para>

<informalexample>
    <screenshot><graphic fileref="screenshots/ask_create_backup_bad.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>
    <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/ask_create_backup_bad.ycp" parse="text"
                          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting>
</informalexample>
<para>this is plainly redundant. This could be done much better like this:</para>

<informalexample>
    <screenshot><graphic fileref="screenshots/ask_create_backup_good.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>
    <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/ask_create_backup_good.ycp" parse="text"
                          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting>
</informalexample>


<para>i.e. concise question, no lyrics around it, clear, plain and simple.</para>
<para>
If you need to provide more background information to the user so he can
understand what tragedy could befall his machine should he chose either
alternative, a headline makes perfect sense for the more experienced user who
gets to this kind of question quite frequently:
</para>
<informalexample>
    <screenshot><graphic fileref="screenshots/ask_resize_windows_partition.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>
    <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/ask_resize_windows_partition.ycp" parse="text"
                          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<note>
<para>This example might be a good candidate for ContinueCancel() - see below</para>
</note>
<para>
If you use headlines, please use them to either
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>classify the type of popup (Error, Warning, ...)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>summarize the question.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
Please DON'T use headlines like "Question" etc. - this doesn't have any
informative value, yet it forces the user to read this useless headline.
</para>
<para>
For all those reasons, most popups come in a generic version where you can pass
a headline ("Headline" is included in the names of those) and a simple version
for general usage.
</para>
</section>
<section>
<title>Predefined Messages</title>
<para>
There are predefined messages for commonly used texts for the dialogs. Use them
when you use the "expert" version of a dialog - don't pass your own messages if
you can avoid it! Not only makes this life easier for our translators (they
need to translate stuff like "Cancel" over and over again), it also gives us a
chance to provide consistent keyboard shortcuts throughout the entire program.
</para>

<example>
<para>Use

<programlisting>
`OpenDialog(
            ...
            `HBox(
:-)               `PushButton( `id(`ok ), `opt(`default), Label::OKButton() ),
                  `PushButton( `id(`retry ), Label::RetryButton() ),
                  `PushButton( `id(`cancel), Label::CancelButton() )
                  )
           )
</programlisting>
and NOT
<programlisting>

`OpenDialog(
            ...
            `HBox(
:-(               `PushButton( `id(`ok ), `opt(`default), _("&amp;OK") ),
                  `PushButton( `id(`retry ), "&amp;Retry"  ),
                  `PushButton( `id(`cancel), "&amp;Cancel" )
                  )
           )
</programlisting>

- even whenever you create your own dialogs.</para>
</example>

<para>
The first part of the name always is the message itself literally ("Retry"),
the suffix indicates the type ("Button") to indicate whether or not it has
a keyboard shortcut. Currently we have "Label::xxxButton" (with keyboard
shortcut) and "Label::xxxMsg" (without shortcut).
</para>

</section>
<section>
<title>When to use what Popup</title>
<section>
<title>Decision Popups - two buttons, return true or false</title>
<para>
For confirmation of possibly dangerous things, use <link linkend="Module_Popup_ContinueCancel">Popup::ContinueCancel</link>.
</para>

<para>
Only when there are two really distinct paths of decision use <link linkend="Module_Popup_YesNo">Popup::YesNo</link>.
- and no, cancelling the entire process doesn't count here - this is no
equivalent decision.
</para>


<para>
The positive case ("Yes" or "Continue") is the default. If you don't like that,
use the generic <link linkend="Module_Popup_AnyQuestion">Popup::AnyQuestion</link> directly and pass `focus_no for the focus
parameter. </para>

<para>
Remember: Only do that for very good reasons - i.e. when it's a really
dangerous decision that typically results in loss of data that can't easily be
restored. 
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>If you need to pass other button labels, think twice. </para></listitem>
<listitem><para>If you really need this, use <link linkend="Module_Popup_AnyQuestion">Popup::AnyQuestion</link>.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
But NEVER use it so simply change the order of default buttons - 
i.e. NEVER create dialogs like this:
</para>
<informalexample>
    <screenshot><graphic fileref="screenshots/ask_format_hard_disk_bad.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>
    <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/ask_format_hard_disk_bad.ycp" parse="text"
                          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting>
</informalexample>
<informalexample>
    <screenshot><graphic fileref="screenshots/ask_show_installation_log_bad.png"></graphic>
    </screenshot>
    <programlisting><xi:include href="examples/ask_show_installation_log_bad.ycp" parse="text"
                          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/></programlisting>
</informalexample>


 </section>
 <section>
 <title>Info Popups - just an "OK" button</title>
<para>
If you can classify a simple message accordingly, use one of</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><link linkend="Module_Popup_Error">Popup::Error</link></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><link linkend="Module_Popup_Warning">Popup::Warning</link></para></listitem>
<listitem><para><link linkend="Module_Popup_Notify">Popup::Notify</link></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
they all have a headline that indicates the type (Error, Warning, Notify).
</para>
<para>
If you can't classify your message, use <link linkend="Module_Popup_Message">Popup::Message</link>.
</para>

<para>
Use <link linkend="Module_Popup_LongText">Popup::LongText</link> to display large amounts of text that might need
scrolling. </para>

</section>
</section>
</section>


