<?xml version="1.0" encoding='ISO-8859-1'?>
<chapter id = "tsig_keys">
  <title>TSIG Keys Management</title>
  <para>
CWMTsigKeys is a widget for CWM that can be used for management
of TSIG keys (that are used for DDNS authentication between
DNS and DHCP servers). It handles all needed functionality.
  </para>
  <para>
Additionally, the module provides functions that can be very useful
for modules that manipulate TSIG keys.
  </para>
  <para>
To create the service start widget, use the
<computeroutput>CWMTsigKeys::CreateWidget</computeroutput> function.
As parameter, it takes a map with settings needed to create the widget
and handle settings on it, returns a map with the widget for CWM. This map
can be used the same way as maps for other widgets.
  </para>

<example id="tsig_keys_basic">
  <title>Usage of the Tsig Keys Management widget</title>
<screen>
        global define void SetKeysInfo (map&lt;string,any&gt;) {...}
        global define map&lt;string,any&gt; GetKeysInfo () {...}

        map&lt;string,any&gt; widget = CWMTsigKeys::CreateWidget ($[
            "get_keys_info" : DhcpServer::GetKeysInfo,
            "set_keys_info" : DhcpServer::SetKeysInfo,
        ]);
 </screen>
</example>
<section>
  <title>Reading and storing TSIG Keys</title>
  <para>
The parameters for service starting are following:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><computeroutput>
"get_keys_info"
      </computeroutput>
is reference to a function with no parameter returning a map with following
keys:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para><computeroutput>
"removed_files"
	  </computeroutput>
lists of strings, file names of files with TSIG keys that were removed
during previous runs of the dialog (just copy of the same value that
passed to "set_keys_info". May be missing.
	  </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para><computeroutput>
"new_files"
	  </computeroutput>
lists of strings, file names of files with TSIG keys that were added
during previous runs of the dialog (just copy of the same value that
passed to "set_keys_info". May be missing.
	  </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para><computeroutput>
"tsig_keys"
	  </computeroutput>
is a list of maps of TSIG keys. Each map is of type string->string, with keys
"key" and "filename" and values key ID resp. file name of the file with the
key.
	  </para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para><computeroutput>
"key_files"
	  </computeroutput>
is an alternative to "tsig_keys". Is used only if "tsig_keys" is missing.
Contains a list of strings, file names of files with TSIG keys.
	  </para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
It is mandatory. "key_files" is used only if "tsig_keys" is missing.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><computeroutput>
"set_keys_info"
      </computeroutput>
is reference to a function with one map parameter containing information
about TSIG keys and return type viod. The map is of type string->any.
should be started at boot and return type void. It is mandatory.
      </para>
      <para>
The map contains all keys mentioned in "get_keys_info" odcumentation.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
</section>
<section>
  <title>Other stuff</title>
  <para>
Other supported parameters are following:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><computeroutput>
"help"
      </computeroutput>
the complete help for the widget. If it is not present, generic help is used
(button labels are patched into the help texts.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
</section>
<section>
  <title>Notes on the widget</title>
  <para>
If "removed_files" or "new_files" is not present in output of "get_keys_info",
then in "set_keys_info" the value contains keys that were added/removed during
the one run of the dialog. Otherwise, added/removed keys are added to the
appropriate variables. The widget takes care that no key is in both of the
variables.
  </para>
  <para>
If keys are specified via "key_files" and some of the files don't contain
any key, these files aren't specified in the variable in the
"set__keys_info". Such files aren't mentioned in "removed_files".
  </para>
</section>
<section>
  <title>Misc. functions</title>
  <para>
The CWMTsigKeys module also offers several functions tightly boud to the
TSIG keys. Following functions are available:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><computeroutput>
list&lt;string&gt; AnalyzeTSIGKeyFile (string filename)
      </computeroutput>
Analyzes the file and return list of all TSIG Key IDs found in the file.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><computeroutput>
list&lt;string&gt; Files2Keys (list&lt;string&gt; filenames)
      </computeroutput>
Analyzes all of the files and returns a list of all TSIG key IDs fount in
the files.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><computeroutput>
list&lt;map&lt;string,string&gt;&gt; Files2KeyMaps
(list&lt;string&gt; filenames)
      </computeroutput>
Analyzes the files and returns a list of the maps of all TSIG keys found in
the files. A TSIG Key map (string->string) contains keys "key" and "filename"
with values Key ID resp. file name of the file.
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
</section>
</chapter>
